<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian letter, containing a graue and godly admonition to such as make separation from the church assemblies in England and elsewhere. VVritten in Latine, by that most Reuerend and learned man, Master Francis Iunius, diuinitie reader at Leyden in Holland, and translated into English, by R G..</title>
            <author>Junius, Franciscus, 1545-1602.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 166384400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7298.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">166384400</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 166384400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2271:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian letter, containing a graue and godly admonition to such as make separation from the church assemblies in England and elsewhere. VVritten in Latine, by that most Reuerend and learned man, Master Francis Iunius, diuinitie reader at Leyden in Holland, and translated into English, by R G..</title>
                  <author>Junius, Franciscus, 1545-1602.</author>
                  <author>R. G., fl. 1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Dexter, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Paules Churchyard, at the Signe of the Brasen Serpent.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B³ (last page blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: text stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Boston Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brownists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191527:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191527:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIAN Letter, containing a graue and godly admonition to ſuch <hi>as make ſeparation from the Church</hi> aſſemblies in England and elſewhere.</p>
            <p>VVritten in Latine, by that moſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend and learned man, Master Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Iunius,</hi> Diuinitie Reader at <hi>Leyden</hi> in <hi>Holland, and tranſlated into Engliſh,</hi> By R G.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed for <hi>Robert Dexter,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe in <hi>Paules</hi> Churchyard, at the Signe of the Braſen Serpent. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:191527:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191527:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCH as of late yeares haue rent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the holie ſeruice of God, vſed in the publique congregations and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of England, being destitute of any ſound warrant from the worde of God, haue ſought from time to time ſo much the more earneſtly (as the manner of ſuch is) to ſhroude themſelues vnder the ſhadowe of humane authoritie. Hence it came to paſſe that maſter <hi>Francis Iunius,</hi> a man of great learning and godlineſſe, was ſolicited by ſome of them (as may appeare by theſe letters enſuing) in the yeare <hi>99.</hi> to be a fauourer of their erronious opinions and of their vnchristian diſordered and vndutifull proceedings: whoſe anſwere, being deliuered by himſelfe to a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and worſhipfull knight, and ſo comming to my handes, I haue preſumed to communicate with thee, by the motion of ſome godly and well diſpoſed, hoping that through the bleſſing of God, and thy prayers it may prooue a good meanes to ſtay ſuch as are wauering, to confirme ſuch as doe ſtand, and to recouer ſuch as are fallen. For although he doe not enter into an exact diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing
<pb facs="tcp:191527:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:191527:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:191527:4"/>
of the queſtion with arguments, obiections, and anſweres: yet he vſeth a very graue and godly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, which is oftentimes of greater fruite, then a long and learned diſputation. And whoſoeuer doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſtudie the booke of God, ſhal finde, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets &amp; Apoſtles do in manie places inſiſt vpon a plaine &amp; ſimple aſseueration of the truth rather the vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> multitude of proofs &amp; argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Beſides, if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſtory of the holy Martyrs of our own Church &amp; others, we may perceiue that by the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d profeſsion of their faith, and ſuffering for the ſame, they haue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified God and aduanced the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt aſwell as others haue done by arguments and reaſons. And yet notwithſtanding if thou do well obſerue theſe letters of maſter <hi>Iunius,</hi> thou ſhalt finde in them not vaine and emptie wordes: but waightie and ſounde reaſons grounded vpon the holie Scriptures of god. Thus praying thee to take theſe firſt fruites of my poore laboures in this kinde in good part, and beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching god to giue a bleſſing hereunto; I bid thee hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily farewell in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lorde, R G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:191527:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Grace mercie and peace from God the father and our <hi>Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> HAVE receiued of late (belooued brethren in Chriſt) a little booke by one of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie; which is intituled, <hi>A confeſſion of faith of ſome Engliſh men baniſhed in Belgia,</hi> and haue knowne your deſire partly by the ſpeach of the ſame meſſenger, partly by the preface of the writing. But as concerning my ſelfe, beloued brethren, whom peraduenture yee haue thought meete to be appealed vnto a part, I verily ſee not how much I can doe in this cauſe, or how I can fit your purpoſe. For I knowe that now long ſince euery man doth abound in his owne ſenſe; and that thoſe that are otherwiſe minded are ſo farre to be borne with, holding the heade and foundation, till the Lord reueale things further vnto them. I know it is my part not to play the buſie body; but that I ſhould ſerue the truth and charitie in my ſtanding and meaſure which the Lord hath beſtowed vpon me, in Chriſtian modeſtie and ſimplicitie, as farre as my ſkil and abilitie wil ſtretch vnto. Certainely when I conſidered more diligently, I thought nothing more commodious or more ſafe both for you and for my ſelfe, publickly in all this matter; then that we ſhould embrace a holy ſilence. Yf there be any thing wherein we be offended, let vs commit our cauſe to the Lord, the author of our faith, and righter of our cauſe. But becauſe after a ſort, you will not ſuffer mee to be ſilent, and to condole in ſecret for the woundes of the
<pb facs="tcp:191527:5"/>
Church, which is rent more then inough, by actions thruſt forth in publick in this our age; I will declare faithfully, and with a good conſcience before God what I thinke: beſeeching him who is author of peace and truthe that he would leade both you and me alike into all trueth according to his promiſe, &amp; alſo diſpoſe each of our mindes and affections to interpret brotherly one anothers requeſtes, anſweres, admonitions, and finally all our duties, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (as it commeth to paſſe, and is incident to man) diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from our ſenſe and taſte. I obſerue therefore that there are three chapters in your little booke, wherein you deſire our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and iudgement. The firſt is that heade of doctrine which you profeſſe in your little booke. The ſecond is the fact whereof yee haue accuſed the Engliſh Churches. Laſtly the third is, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion which you inferre by comparing that your doctrine with that practiſe of England; namely that yee cannot with good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience entertaine a communion with thoſe Churches, but that yee doe abhorre them with all your heartes. Therefore I will ſpeak briefely of theſe 3. things, entreating you brotherly to take my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere in good part. I maruell that the point of doctrine, or little booke of your confeſſion, beloued brethren, is ſent ouer to me: I maruell that it was ſent ouer to all the ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of holy Scriptures in all Chriſtian Vniuerſities; for if there be a certaine conſent of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine as you pretend it, truely I do not ſee what need there was, that you ſhould ſet forth a newe confeſſion in this preſent of holy and auncient doctrine. But if there be a diſſention peraduenture in the doctrine, or rather a difference, the ſame ought not to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, if ſo be that yee thought it neceſſarie, that your doctrine ſhould be declared. Beſides, in that you ſend to mee; yea that you ſend to the publicke viewe of the whole Church. I maruell, brethren, yea I greatly maruell, what your meaning ſhould bee, both in reſpect of the ende and the fact. For if yee haue ſet it foorth to that end, that yee might purge your ſelues, I pray you brethren, wherefore doe yee deſire, to purge your ſelues with ſo many ſoules; who neuer could knowe you as yet to bee accuſed; which can neuer take knowledge of the right or wrong of your accuſation; and who are not called vnto it by any lawfull means;
<pb facs="tcp:191527:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and (that which is worſe) wherfore would yee haue that done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo many enemies to God and the Church, who thirſt after nothing ſo much as the bloode of the Church of God, and doe reioyce that we vndiſcreetly do cauſe a publiſhing of theſe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds that by theſe wounds they might ſpoyle the Church, that pretious bodie of Chriſt, of the bloode of veritie, and iuyce of charitie. Finally, why doe yee this before ſo many weake ones, who not yet knowing, that yee are borne (as I may ſo ſay) are offended, rather with a carcaſſelike ſtink of ſchiſmes in the Church, before they knowe certainely the bodie whereunto they may cleaue? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las brethren, is your purgation ſo much worth vnto you that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the publicke good of the Church ſhould bee brought into ſo greate danger. A Chriſtian an humble, and godly minde ought to bee otherwiſe affected, and ſetting aſide the reſpect of their owne priuate good, inſtantly ſo to determine, that the earth ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſwallowe them vp (as the Poet ſaith) and let mee rather bee accurſed for my brethren, then that by me, and for my credit ſake one of theſe little ones ſhould be offended and kept from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Chriſt, and abiding in Chriſt my Sauiour. Verily let what will of my eſtimation goe to wracke, who am a Chriſtian, let me be trampled vnder all mens feete, ſo that by my fact, I take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from Chriſt, no not the leaſt thing from his bodie. And that you my brethren, ſhould determine and reſolue, to bend all your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſels to this end; I am as ſtrongly perſwaded, as he that is moſt. But what end haue yee in common? alas for griefe in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar caſe (pardon if I ſpeake more freely, for yee would haue me to ſpeake) yee ſeeme to haue erred: for herein, if I ſee any thing, the contemplation of your particular cauſe hath deceiued you, which thing yee your ſelues without doubt will marke if ye would goe a little from that your particular ſenſe.</p>
            <p>I haue ſhewed that there is ſome errour in that end. Let vs come to the fact. In the fact yee haue framed a purgation of your ſelues. That thing is denyed to none, if there ſhall be a cauſe, if a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, if a place, if a time. But wherefore with mee brethren, who doe neither heare theſe accuſations of yours; neither if I ſhould heare them would I receiue them raſhly? Wherefore in publick?
<pb facs="tcp:191527:6"/>
where yee knowe that it falleth out for the moſt part, that they who purge themſelues, before they be accuſed, eyther betray the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, eyther raiſe ſuch ſuſpicions againſt themſelues as they can not afterward eaſily waſh away. Yee knowe that the publicke voice is neither a iuſt iudge oftentimes, nor at any time almoſt a lawfull Iudge; ſo greatly doth malice preuaile and beare ſway in the publicke. Therefore yee appeale to theſe Iudges, who can neither iudge, nor take knowledge: finally, they are not onely no Iudges, but not ſo much as witneſſes: ſo the priuate cauſe is not furthered, and the publique is many waies hindered. Yee will ſay then, who ſhall bee? What iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, what witneſſes ſhall wee appeale vnto? Your owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face ſhall anſwere yee for me. For when ye pronounce that ye haue found a place of reſt by the mercy of God in theſe places (ye doe acknowledge I thinke your owne words) ye plainely ſignifie two things. One, that if ye haue found a place of reſt, ye ſhall doe wiſely, if ye doe not ſtirre, where ye may be in quiet. The other that where you haue a lodging, and a quiet ſeate that there yee muſt alſo be iudged, there you muſt receiue the iudgement of your doctrine and faith, if ye will haue the ſame lawfully knowne and approoued. Ye are in a Church furniſhed with the ſeruants of God, whoſe pietie, learning, and brotherly loue to the members of Chriſt good men doe know. It is an vnlawfull courſe verily, to omit thoſe among whom yee are and to appeale to another Church, or to the whole publike ſtate, or to me who am a weake member therein, either in part, or in common. This order is god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, iuſt, lawfull, and tendeth to the peace, and edification, which you ought firſt, modeſtly to regard, and to which I being a weake brother, am bounden by brotherly duetie, to all my brethren, that goe aſtray, and not to be caried headlong, and to ruſh vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the knowledge of theſe things by this meanes offred; beſides all equitie and good order. Till ye ſhall doe that, I admoniſh, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, pray, and beſeech by the moſt ſacred &amp; holy name of Chriſt, that ye would not appeale to me, neither to any other, neither to the whole Church: for by this prepoſterous courſe (as we may ſo ſay) ye do not disburthen your ſelues, as ye thinke, of enuy and
<pb facs="tcp:191527:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
blame (if there be any) but ye doe burthen your owne cauſe, to which I will bring no preiudice. Let them ſpeake firſt, with whom yee ſoiourne, whom yee deny not to be your brethren. But if peraduenture they ſhall not ſatiſfie you, or yee ſhall not ſatiſfie them, then let a new courſe be taken by lawfull order. This no good man will denie, but till this be attempted, it will be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable to you, and hurtfull to the Church, to take another courſe. But neither I, nor my Colleagues, nor other wiſe men, will euer be ſo impudent as to preuent or take this thing out of the hands of them, to whom the knowledge thereof doth of right appertaine. And ſo much of the doctrine. I come to the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which yee vſe, againſt the Church of England, as yee write in this accuſation beloued brethren, I doe louingly entreat you, that yee would not take it in ill part, if I doe admoniſh yee, of a few things which I thinke, I may of right doe, firſt, what need is there, that yee ſhould accuſe them? Yee haue giuen place, yee haue (as wee may ſo ſpeake) paſſed ouer into another Court, wherefore haue yee giuen place? No body deſireth to know, or doth trouble yee. If wrong be done you, in England (that I may grant it that is done, for it belongeth not to me, to affirme or deny who haue not knowne it) yet they doe not proſecute this iniury yee being departed from them. What compelleth you to be mooued, and to take vpon you, the burthen of accuſation? Why are yee not quiet being without the daunger of any hurt? Why doe yee not rather paſſe ouer the iniury that is paſt? Why doe yee not rather beare it (if there be yet any hope in ſilence) then to mooue, that which is in reſt? It is plainely a Chriſtian part, if yee beare it, and a prudent part, if you abſtaine from ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the euill that is well appeaſed, an impudent thing, if yee doe contrariwiſe. And to what end I pray you is it? To the end that you might purge your ſelues. But here is no man that doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate anew, or lay theſe accuſations againſt you. Wherefore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth this purgation? that yee may be euen with them againſt whom yee complaine. But this is not the part of a Chriſtian. I doe not thinke that this is your meaning. Is it to reforme them? This indeed is an holy endeuour. But if yee could not doe this,
<pb facs="tcp:191527:7"/>
when yee were preſent, conſider what yee may doe when yee are abſent. But firſt of all conſider with your ſelues, by what meanes yee take this way, namely to accuſe to me, to other to a publike place in the theatre of the Church, in the circle of the world. Ah beloued brethren, was it euer heard of, that any priuate man (to ſay nothing of a great communitie) was euer amended by this courſe. Further conſider I pray you before whom yee bring theſe things, I will ſay of my ſelfe, to whom alone yee will commit this your little booke; I know not whether in this your little booke yee appeale to me, as to an interceſſor, or examiner, or a Iudge. For if as an interceſſor, were it not better that your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints were kept ſecret, then layed open (which tendeth to reproch) and the Church of Chriſt, innumerable ſoules, weake, ſtrangers, to be beaten with the types of your impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is moſt manifeſt, that they againſt whom yee deale, will be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked by theſe grieuous things. If as an examiner, by what right can I doe it? who haue no lawfull authority from God, from the Church, from the Magiſtrate, or from both the parties: neither if it ſhould be committed, would I eaſily accept it; I am ſo priuie to my ſelfe, of my owne inſufficiencie: for who am I? or what am I? that I ſhould be able, throughly to ſee euery particular thing, concerning you, and them, which are required to a iuſt examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this the right courſe of examination doth require, otherwiſe (as <hi>Seneca</hi> wiſely faith) he that iudgeth one party being not heard, albeit he iudgeth that which is right, yet he is vniuſt. Yee are not a little deceiued in this your iudgement beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: Yee almoſt do me an iniury, when ye call me to be a buſie body, or think that I wil take vpon me the part of an examiner, or (that which is more ſubiect to enuie and farre from duetie) of a Iudge. And brethren, that which I ſay of my ſelfe, thinke that is the anſwere of other brethren in Churches and Vniuerſities. No wiſe man will eaſily goe downe the ſteps, or clime vp to the ſeate of iudgement. Concerning your faith and doctrine ſomething may be ſaid, if you expound it, and if the thing be done in order. For touching the accuſation of your countreymen, and of matters paſſed to and fro; no wiſe man by my conſent, wil take vpon him the burthen of iudging. And for Gods ſake, conſider the euent of
<pb facs="tcp:191527:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this fact. For I pray you whom would it profit if that were done which yee deſire? Certainly neither would it profit you nor them, nor theſe with whom ye ſoiourne, nor the Church of God. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe whom would it not hurt? This thing would ſet you more on fire: it would more alienate them whom yee iniuriouſly tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to be enſtranged from you. For this is not the way of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, nor of informing, nor of ſeeking reconciliation. To rent the good men whoſe hoſpitality yee doe commodiouſly vſe, or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them from you, or amongſt themſelues (which duetie they haue not deſerued of you by their hoſpitalitie) will make that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent man which ſhould vſurpe this authoritie a ſcorne to ill tongues, while good men would pittie his vaine labour, and your vaine expectation. Laſtly (that I may alſo adde this, marke bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, how ſincerely and brotherly I deale with you) albeit you might and would lawfully both of your faith which yee declare and alſo to giue ſentence of the fact of the accuſation which yee bend againſt your Countreymen: Yet yee by this courſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of dealing haue taken from me that which yee require tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching your fact. Ye will maruaile perhaps at that which I ſay, and yet it is ſo. For you doe ſo require my iudgement as you doe alſo require the iudgement of all Students and Vniuerſities in common; then you doe not deſire that I ſhould doe it alone: but if particularly, doe you thinke that any of vs will be ſo mad, that when the iudgement of ſo many good men and diligence is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſome one <hi>Palaemon</hi> ſhould take vpon him the chiefeſt parts: and ſhould by him ſelfe ſpeake of that thing, which is required of ſo many as learned, yea better learned, and better furniſhed with pietie, iudgement, and experience, which requireth a ſerious conſultation, an holy communication, and a ripe in offenſiue iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But of the third thing what ſhall I ſay? touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion which you draw from thence, that is, from thoſe premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, if I ſhall yet determine any thing on either ſide, it were vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vniuſt. Wherefore? I verily brethren ſuſpend my iudgement in this cauſe euen as God &amp; nature, &amp; reaſon, and al lawes command me to do. Ye know the cauſes by theſe things which ye haue now read, &amp; ſhal learne beſides by other things which God ſhal mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto you (I hope) by the ſpirit of trueth and wiſdome. I ought
<pb facs="tcp:191527:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not to iudge with my ſelfe of matters vnknowne, at leaſt not ſo euident, neither yet with ſuch forward boldneſſe to pronounce among you or others, the matter being not ſufficiently manifeſt to my ſelfe. God knoweth and iudgeth them which ſtand or fall, as many as are his ſeruants. Otherwiſe I truſt yee are not ignorant that there are three things which euen from the verie infancie of the Church, the holy fathers would haue to be diſtinguiſhed by the word of God, among the people of God; namely, faith or doctrine, conuerſation or manners, and the order of diſcipline. And all wiſe men haue taught that with one conſent, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to poſteritie, that where the foundation of the truth of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine remaineth, which is the piller of ſaluation although with moſt corrupt manners and diſcipline, there the Church remaineth, &amp; that no man ought raſhly to ſeparate himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Church (whiles he may tarry in it without ſhipwracke of faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) or take from it the name of a Church, eſpecially ſeeing euery Church conſiſteth of Paſtors and flockes, which if ſome Paſtors or Prelates trouble, yet it is vnmeete that this name either ſhould be taken away from the other Paſtors, which Chriſt doth witneſſe by the doctrine of truth, or from the flocke which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his owne bloode, and doth daily ſanctifie with the waſhing of the newe birth by the worde. This ought to be ſufficient for you if any thing offend you at home. Now the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly &amp; mercifull prouidence of God hath prouided for you elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. Certainely whiles yee inueigh againſt thoſe Churches, yee ſhal make that your cauſe neuer the better, neither more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable with good men: which thing if yee haue not yet conſidered and conceiued by my aduiſe and counſell, and by the admonition of thoſe which wiſh you wel; experience it ſelfe at laſt (God grant it be not to late, and informe you in good) will prooue all theſe things vnto you. For by the trueth of doctrine, holineſſe of life, by the worke of faith and patience, and by the dueties of charitie e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen towards them of whome yee profeſſe that yee are wronged, yee ſhall rather approoue your ſelues and your cauſe, then by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryes and publiſhing of writings, euen as our Sauiour is ſaide to bring iudgement to victorie not by filling the ſtreetes with ſhou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:191527:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and clamours, but by blowing gently into the ſmoking flax and tender handling the bruiſed reede: which thinges ſeeing they be ſo, I beſeech you moſt louing brethren in Chriſt by that moſt holie name of Chriſt which yee profeſſe, by thoſe bowels of mercie, wherewith Chriſt hath embraced vs from on high, that yee would thinke of another courſe, that yee would take another way to edification to ſaluation to peace. If there be any conſent ſhake not your faith, which is not to be winnowed againe by new reaſons. This courſe is ſuſpitious, but if it muſt neede be ſifted let it ſuffice you that it be firſt approoued by thoſe ſeruants of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whome yee dwell: this is certainely a lawfull courſe: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue the former iniuries if any haue beene by Chriſtian charitie to them from whom yee haue receiued the ſame, &amp; hide them from others by Chriſtian wiſdome. There is no feare, that by ſo doing yee ſhall ſuffer violence: God will enlarge your harts by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of charitie moſt commodiouſly. Looke to your ſelues that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercomming al ſharpneſſe and al bitterneſſe of minde yee may be acceptable to Chriſt and profitable to the Church; and that the odour of your pietie may be ſpread in ſpeach, in life, in order to all the godly moſt ſweetely without the ſtench of enmitie and ſchiſme. Iudge not that yee be not iudged: But abſtaine from thoſe heauie concluſions and determinations (as they call them) againſt other men, neither labour either to get Abetters or partakers in that your former iudgement (which would be ſaide in you to be a ſpice of faction in them of impudencie, or elſe to drawe them to an vnſeaſonable, vnciuill, inconuenient or dangerous deliuerie of opinions. Pitie your ſelues I beſeech you (moſt louing brethren) and the whole flocke which is gathered among you; haue pittie of them whome thorough error &amp; infirmitie yee cry out be hurt. Pitie your entertainers among whome it were a moſt iniurious thing that ye ſhould ſowe theſe tares; eſpecially being admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And it would be a greate indignitie by clamours and writings to brede in them ſuſpicions and ſiniſter opinions, eyther of your ſelues or of thoſe your aduerſaries (as you count them) or els of both. Finally pitie the Church of Chriſt, which verily it is not comely, nor expedient neither in any caſe tolerable among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:191527:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:191527:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:191527:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and greeuous wounds which are giuen vnto it to be further gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with this particular wound. So let God almightie loue you and Ieſus Chriſt that moſt mercifull Lord, and our Sauiour be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto you. And if I ſhall be able to doe any good in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke cauſe and in your cauſe: aſſure your ſelues that I will ſpare no diligence, no labour, no paines; that you with vs and all togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be filled with ſanctimony (without which none ſhall ſee God) with the good things of the Lord in his houſe, and before his face. And the God of peace which hath raiſed from the dead our Lord Ieſus that great ſheepeheard of the ſheepe, by the blood of the eternall couenant, make you perfect in euery good worke to doe his will, working in you, that which is acceptable in his ſight by Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be glorie for euer and euer, Amen. And I pray you brethren ſuffer this word of exhortation, which I haue briefely written vnto you. The grace of God be with you all, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. From <hi>Leyden</hi> this Saturday the 9. of <hi>Ianuary.</hi> 1599.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the Lord</hi> Francis Iunius.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:191527:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
